皆さん、こんにちはDan Reecerです
私はAcalaのgrowth VPとして働いています。
私がAcalaチームに参加してから2年になります。
約2年位なりますが、
その前はWeb3 Foundationにいました。
で、PolkadotとKusamaのローンチに携わっていました。
今日は手短にお話ししたいと思います。
もしかしたら早口になるかもしれませんが、
早口になるかもしれませんが、
内容を概要部分に絞って
PolkadotとKusamaの
パラチェーンオークションと
クラウドローンの簡単な仕組みについて
お話したいと思います。
ご存知のように、
PolkadotやKusamaは、
パラチェーンと呼ばれる
複数のブロックチェーンを
集約して機能する事ができる
マルチチェーンエコシステムです。
将来的にはPolkadotにも
kusamaにも100個以上のパラチェーンが
存在する様になるでしょうが、
現状はどちらにも
パラチェーンは存在していません。
そこで今日は、
この図の中の小さな四角い枠の一つとして、
実際にスロットを獲得する方法についてお話します。
kusamaの最初のパラチェーンや
polkadotの最初のパラチェーンになるには
どうすればいいのか、
そのプロセスが
クラウドローンと
パラチェーンオークションです。
これがそのタイムラインです。
ここでは、クラウドローンが
先に来ることがわかりますが、
これについては
後ほど説明します。
メインイベントは、白地で示されている
パラチェーンオークションです。
これは複数のパラチェインチームが、
オークションでの勝利を目指して
互いに競い合うものです。
オークションに勝利してこの枠を獲得すると、
正式にKusamaやPolkadotの
パラチェーンとして登録されます。
このプロセスを経て、
プロジェクトはようやく
アプリケーションを正式に
ローンチすることができるというわけです。
これは基本的な
これらが基本的な
polkadotとKusamaの
パラチェーンオークションに関する
ビジョンとなります。そして、
チームが獲得したスロットの終了時間の部分を
見ていただきたいのですが、チームがそのスロットを獲得した後に、
クラウドローンの資金が貢献者に還元されるという
イベントが発生しているのがわかりますね。
次の数枚のスライドで、
この部分を説明します。
パラチェーンオークションに関しては、
クラウドローンを理解する前に
しっかり把握しておく必要があるので、
この点について少し話しましょう。
パラチェーンスロットオークションとは、
先ほど申し上げたように、
チームが互いに競い合って
1つのスロットを獲得しようとするもので、
各オークションは最終的に1つのスロットを
獲得する為に争うことになります。
チームによってはもっと短い期間で
入札することも可能ですが、
ここではシンプルに
最大値を想定してみましょう。
オークションに参加するチームには、
実際の入札方法や
入札に使用する資金について、
2つの選択肢があります。
まず、
kusamaのように
1つのアカウントを持っていて、
オークションに使用できるKSMの
保有量があり、
コミュニティを巻き込む必要がない場合は、
1つの選択肢となるでしょう。
The more frequent and more
likely scenario
will be number two here, which is using
the crowdloan module
so in this case you're actually
crowdsourcing KSM in the case of Kusama
or crowdsourcing DOT
from your community and you're
basically crowdsourcing this so that you
can use that
in the parachain slot auction.
How often will this happen? So
Parachain auctions will be done
one at a time but it's looking like
these will be about every two weeks so
in the Polkadot and Kusama ecosystem
these things will be happening on an
ongoing basis for the foreseeable future
so crowdloans first of all
like i said are used
for the opening bid in an auction so
teams will
crowdsource these tokens and then use
them in that parachain auction at the
next step.
If you're a user and you contribute KSM
to a Kusama parachain or if you
contribute DOT to a Polkadot parachain
you're essentially agreeing to locking
those tokens for the duration of that
parachain slot.
In the example that I used earlier
let's assume 24 months
then after 24 months your original
principle is returned back to you so
it's essentially no loss and a much more
ethical model
than we've seen in the past with things
like ICOs because in this case
you really hold the team accountable for
actually delivering on their
vision in their white paper because they
need to add value to their network
because they're actually not raising
any funds directly from you as the
community member.
Last, I kind of hinted at this
just now but
the funds that are contributed in
KSM or in DOT
are never touched by the team so there's
no worries about
teams raising money and running away
with it not delivering on what they
promised. All
the interests are really aligned here
and the team is really held accountable.
In the crowdloan,
this is kind of what it looks like.
You've got multiple teams
crowdsourcing KSM or DOT from their
communities
and that leads into the paratrain slot
auction.
Everything that was raised in that
crowdloan stage is
is not accessible to the team but
they can actually use that
in their parachain slot auction. So you
can think of it like a poker table
at the beginning of the auction all
these teams will basically go all in
with the funds that they raised in
their crowdloan.
Then how do we determine the winner?
When the auction starts we will know the
open time
here in the green, and we will know the
close time in the orange over here
and the most exciting point will be when
we hit this close time
the Kusama or Polkadot relay chain
itself will randomly select a time
that determines the end time, this red
bar here. So in this
example you've got Parachain B bidding,
Parachain C bidding,
Parachain A bidding.... E and F
beat A in terms of number of KSM but the
winner was determined at this red line
so
the highest bidder was Parachain A.
This is called an unpermissioned candle auction
and it incentivizes teams to bid
as high as they can as early as they can
instead of waiting until the end like
you might have seen on ebay
where people try to
snipe at the end and get the highest bid.
This is a full walkthrough of this
whole process. You've got
users over here contributing KSM they
contribute in this example to Karura
500,000 KSM. Then Karua
wins the first slot on Kusama and then
begins its launch process so
all of the KSM that was crowdsourced in
this original
crowdloan period is then locked in the
core
Kusama relay chain and then KAR
is then distributed, the native token of
Karura (KAR) is distributed to the
crowdloan contributors
and then at the same time
Karura is also launching so
the Karura stablecoin, the liquid KSM staking,
as well as
the Karura AMM-DEX, the Karura DEX
all go live on top of Karura
when this happens. At the end of
the parachain slot all of the KSM is
returned to the
supporters. Now the
last question that people sometimes
have is: 'What happens at the end of that
slot?' In this example, let's say
that it was a one-year parachain slot
the KSM is returned to the original
crowdloan supporters and then there's
three options for
any team to kind of maintain their
access to the relay chain.
First is to host another crowdloan and
do another parachain auction,
second is to self fund. Karura and
Acala will both have a decentralized
sovereign wealth fund
and over time that will
continue to build and build
so that we can become sovereign and
self-sustainable and actually
bid with our own treasury our own
sovereign wealth fund
for future slots, and then the third
option
there's probably several wiki articles
and videos that you could watch
about this but, the other option is
to become a parathread, which
just means that you have a little
bit less access..
less frequent access to the relay
chain itself.
So that's it in about eight minutes.
Hopefully you learned something. Let me
know if you have any questions.
Thank you, bye.